<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brefe exhortation set fourthe by the vnprofitable seruant of Iesu christ, Paule Bushe late bishop of Brystowe, to one Margarete Burges wyfe to Ihon Burges, clotheare of kyngeswode in the Countie of Wilshere.</title>
            <author>Bush, Paul, 1490-1558.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1556</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17339</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4184</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118871</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854078</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854078</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19485</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17339)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19485)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 413:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brefe exhortation set fourthe by the vnprofitable seruant of Iesu christ, Paule Bushe late bishop of Brystowe, to one Margarete Burges wyfe to Ihon Burges, clotheare of kyngeswode in the Countie of Wilshere.</title>
                  <author>Bush, Paul, 1490-1558.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In Powles Churchyard at the sygne of the Holye Ghoste by Ihon Cawoode, printer to the king and Quenes Maiesties,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1556]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer from colophon. Date of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An exhortation.</note>
                  <note>End of text dated 7 August 1556-STC.</note>
                  <note>An exhortation to give up Protestant heresies.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Real presence --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19485:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19485:1"/>
            <p>¶ A brefe exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation ſet fourthe by the vnprofitable ſeruant of Ieſu chriſt, Paule Buſhe, late bi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhop of Bryſtowe, to one Margarete Burges wyfe to Ihon Burges, clotheare of kyngeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wode in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhere.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>printer's device of John Cawood, a compartment with Royal Arms at top, supported by a horned male figure and a female figure; at the bottom a crowned figure holding a cross over a lion and a lamb (not in McKerrow)</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:19485:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19485:2"/>
            <head>An exhortation.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>Early beloued ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in Chryſte, at our late being to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in our ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye worſhyppeful frendes houſe in the countie of Gloceſter, at a ſupper meale, with diuerſe other of worthye reputation (whiche was the fyrſt and laſt tyme that euer I ſawe you or ſpake wyth you) And that tyme and ther by oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>caſyon as we ſate at the table (yf you call to your memorye) we entrede into a lytle talke, and afterward continued the ſame ſtandyng at a wyndow, whych talke albeit it was but breife and ſhorte, yet the ſame (as our lorde knoweth) was more than Inough to declare to me, not onely your hygh pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tended
<pb facs="tcp:19485:3"/> knowledge, but alſo your much ignoraunce which I do not a lytle in my harte la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, for I perceyue you haue to litle knowlege and to much ignoraunce. For in verye dede, for lacke of the vertue of meke<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, and the ſpyryte of truthe, (whych teacheth al goodnes) it appereth that blynde igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, permyxte with arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancye, hath greately ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed your ſences, muche like as the obfuſked and darke cloudes of the fyrmament, doo many times ſhadowe and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenebrate the radiaunt &amp; clere ſhynyng beames of the ſonne. And this commeth (yf you ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyſe your ſelfe well) thorough the wycked arte and crafte of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> enemye the deuyll,
<pb facs="tcp:19485:3"/> whiche goeth alwaye aboute to ſhadowe the truth of gods moſt holye word, and the true vnderſtandynge of the ſame, namelye from them whyche haue profeſſed the Catholyke fayth, to brynge them into the daungerous whyrlepoole of wycked ignoraunce, yea and many tymes he playeth wyth them, muche lyke as doeth the miller with his horſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> drawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his mille: for whan he hath made hys horſe blynde that he canne not ſe nor perceyue hys waye by the meanes of a vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarde of leather that he coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth hys face with all, than he maketh hym continuallye all day longe, to go round aboute keping one trade, as thoughe he wente fourthe ryghte the
<pb facs="tcp:19485:4"/> ſtrayte waye. And at euenyng whan he commeth to his ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, than he ſhall haue for hys prauendere, the worſte of hys labour, that is a quantytye of courſe branne, or a boolle full of drowſye draffe, Such is his rewarde for his blinde trauel. And euen thus fareth the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyll with the weake and feble chryſtyans, for whan he goeth aboute to gryende the worde of god in his deuylleſhe mylle of ſciſmaticall and heretycall Doctryne, than becauſe the weake and feble chryſtians, ſhoulde not perceyue the fyne meale of gods word, from the roughe and groſſe branne of wicked doctrine, he goeth and maketh them blynde with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> mauncye, &amp; ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>the them, with
<pb facs="tcp:19485:4"/> gret arrogancy &amp; wyth much pryde, to maintaine ther euyll conceiued opinions, makinge them to beleue that they be in the ryghte ſtrayghte waye. And ſo in concluſyon he bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth them to hys fylthye and ſtynkynge ſtable, there perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuallye to be fedde wyth the roughe and courſe prauender of euerlaſtyng payne and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Mat. xxii.</note> where ſhalbe weapyng and gnaſſhyng of teath. This is the rewarde that he prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for the arrogaunte igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauntes, whych wyll and doo defend their wicked and dam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nable opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s with their raſhe temeryte, and wyll not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed to folowe and beleue the doctrynes, decrees, and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terminations, which the vny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſal church of Chryſt throgh
<pb facs="tcp:19485:5"/> oute the whole worlde, dothe confeſſe and acknowledge. And therfore ſuche arrogaunt ignoraunce in a chriſtian man oughte muche to be reproued and diſprayſed, namely when he ſhall ſo greatly erre, that he thynketh hym ſelfe lerned and to knowe much, when in very dede he is nether learned nor knoweth any thyng at al, and yet ſtoughtly and arrogantlie many times ſuch perſons will not ſtycke wyth muche impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, to approue and verefye that thynge whyche is falſe, and vtterlye and craftelye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nege and denye (wyth tothe and nayle as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prouerbe ſaith) that thyng which is moſt true</p>
            <p>Thys is not onelye a greate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and a wycked errour in
<pb facs="tcp:19485:5"/> a chryſtyan man, but alſo it is ſuch a pernicious and a damp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nable ſynne in the ſyghte and preſence of GOD, that it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyreth noo leſſe than euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng payne and poniſhment. And therefore ſuch arrogante ignoraunce ought much to be feared and eſchewed, whyche procedeth of a ka<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kered malice, towardes God and his truth, and is the ſpecyalle cauſe, of mans greate blyndenes, that he cannotte conceyue the true ſence and meanynge, of Gods moſt holy word. And thys the wyſe man approueth in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde Chapiter of hys boke,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sap.</hi> 2.</note> where he ſayeth. The vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye goo aſtray, and their owne malyce hath blynded them. And the worthy auncient doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toure
<pb facs="tcp:19485:6"/> Chryſoſtome ſayeth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo,<note place="margin">Omel. xli opera im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periorum</note> that ignoraunce of the kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of truth, can be no excuſe of condempnatyon, namelye whan a man by occaſion, may receaue and fynde knowledge yf he had good and towarde mynde to learne. And alſo the noble doctor, &amp; pyller of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes churche,<note place="margin">Sc. lxxviii De. Ver. Domi</note> Saynte Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyne ſayeth lykewyſe, that a wycked man hatethe the true vnderſtandyng, and ſomtime agayne of a peruerte mynd he fearethe to knowe or vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, becauſe he wyll not be conſtrayned afterwarde, to do and folowe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thing which he knoweth. Of ſuche Dauyd in his Pſalmeſte dothe prono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ke and ſaye.<note place="margin">Pſa. xxxv</note> The wycked <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> not be inſtructed, that he
<pb facs="tcp:19485:6"/> might do good. And this igno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raunce (as I ſayd before) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedeth of an arrogant malyce, and of a ſpeciall contempte to be taught or learned the true catholyke doctrine. For whan they be once noeffled in error they be loth to be plucke from there owne wycked concey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued opinions, to knowe God and his infallible truth, which is the verye lyght and ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of there ſoules, their arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant pryde to maintaine their own blind ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is ſo gret And therfore mooſte louynge ſyſter (to be ſhorte) I exhorte you in the bowels of our lorde Ieſu Chriſte, vtterlye to repel fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you that wicked mayſtres and mayntayner of all perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious doctrine (I meane your
<pb facs="tcp:19485:7"/> arrogancye) whych ſo muche puffethe vp youre ignoraunte mynde, that it maketh you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that you are fully inſtruct and perfectlye learned, wyth the readyng of your Englyſhe Pamflettes, and yet ſhe great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye deceaueth you, as I truſte hereafter you wyll no leſſe con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe and acknowledge. For I aſſure you, yf you haue not the vertue of mekenes to vnclaſpe the booke of gods word vnto you, and in the readyng of the ſame, the holy ghoſt to be your teacher, your labor and ſtudye ſhalbe alwaye fruſtrate and in vayne, and your knowledge, no knowledge at al. The wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thye Prophete Kyng Dauyd, albeit he was hyghe inſpyred (by inſtincte diuyne) wyth the
<pb facs="tcp:19485:7"/> holly ſpiryte of truthe and alſo the gyfte of mekenes, yet he de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyſted not (wyth the ſame ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte and gyfte) continually to praye to almightye GOD (as one not ſatyſfyed) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he myght haue from time to time a more deper and a more perfecte vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandyng and knowledge of hym and of hys moſte holye worde. And amonge other of hys deuyne oracles, thus he prayed and ſayde.<note place="margin">Pſa. cxiii</note> O Lorde geue me vnderſtandynge, and I ſhall diligently ſeke out thy lawe, yea and I ſhall kepe it with my whole harte. Let my ſupplycatyon O Lorde, come before thy preſence, and geue me vnderſtandyng according vnto thy worde. And agayne, O Lorde teache me goodnes,
<pb facs="tcp:19485:8"/> diſciplyne, and knowledge, for I went wronge, and therfore nowe I haue kept thy worde. Theſe wordes (O Lorde geue me vnderſtanding) ſo often in culcat and ſo many tymes ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, do no leſſe then euidently declare thys holye Prophetes humble hart, and earneſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre and meanynge, how glad he was to be taught, howe de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyrous he was to learne, and how wyllyng he was to haue vnderſtandynge, and not to ſtand in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> defence of his owne iudgement, as the ſturdy and blynde ignorauntes do. And therefore thys holeſome leſſon (louynge Syſter in Chryſt) I wolde wyſhe you to learne of thys moſte godlye Prophete, and with a ſtedfaſt harte and
<pb facs="tcp:19485:8"/> a faythefull mynde to embrace the ſame. And than no doute you ſhall be well aſſured, God wyll poure into you (as he did into hym out of hys plentifull treaſures) the true vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of hys moſte holly word, euen as our hollye mother the Church techeth and beleueth. For his dyuyne word may not be taken, nether yet expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded after the raſſhe fantaſtycall myndes of the blynd and igno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raunte, but after the true and ſyncere meaning of the holye Apoſtles, bleſſed martirs, and worthye fathers and rulers of Chryſtes mooſte catholyke Churche, from whome and by whome the chryſtian congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, hath alwaye bene ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and gouerned, euer ſythen
<pb facs="tcp:19485:9"/> the deathe and paſſion of oure Sauyour Ieſu Chryſte. And therfore let no other doctryne then theirs lede you, trade you or inſtructe you in the truth of goddes mooſte lyuely worde, for yf you be otherwiſe ſcoled, or yf you ſtande to your owne iudgemente, or yf you be wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to youre owne erronious opynions, then wyl the ſpirite of truethe flee farre from you, and leaue you alone to youre ſelfe, as barren as the wythe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red fygge tree.<note place="margin">Mat. xxi.</note> Nowe to come to the matter which I entend (thoroughe goddes myghte) to wryght to you of. As farre as I doo remember, the lytle talke whyche we entred into, and not fyniſhed by reaſone of your departure, ſend for by
<pb facs="tcp:19485:9"/> the worſhypfull Lad ye of the houſe, and your other neygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures and frendes whyche you came in companye wyth all) was thys, that the bleſſed bodye of oure Sauiour Ieſu Chryſte, cannot be preſentlye here in earth, and alſo in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen at one time and together. O lytel faythe, If this youre ſaying ſhould be true (as it is playne falſe) than in vayne were oure chryſtyan religyon. But you ſhall clerely be putte out of doute, and playnely vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that our fyrme faith and beleue is grounded, foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and rered vpon the head corner ſtone, electe, and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that is vpon Chryſt him ſelfe, in whoſe mouth was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer fraude ne guyle fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19485:10"/> And he that beleuethe in hym (ſayth Saynt Peter) ſhal not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>founded. Therefore vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which beleue he is precius but to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which beleue not he is a ſtone to ſtomble at, and a rocke to offend them that ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at the worde, and beleaue not that, where on they were ſet. And therefore now ſeynge that chryſte our Sauioure is the truth,<note place="margin">Iho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. xiiii</note> and alſo the auctour of all truthe, as he ſaythe hym ſelfe, I am the way, the truthe and the lyfe, who than dare be ſo bolde to denaye that thinge which he affyrmeth and appro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth. For he hym ſelfe ſayde at his moſte godlye maundye (in the preſence of al his diſciples) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hys bleſſed Bodye was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d there really preſente <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e fourmes of breade
<pb facs="tcp:19485:10"/> and wyne. And this the holye Euangelyſt Saynt Mathew in hys Goſpell, declarethe in wordes euydent and playne,<note place="margin">Ma. xx.</note> where he thus ſayeth. As they were eating, Ieſus toke brede and when he had geuen than<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, he brake it, and gaue it to hys diſciples and ſayde. Take eate, this is my bodye. And he toke the cuppe, and whan he had geuen thankes, he gaue it to them ſaying. Drynke you al of this, for this is my bloude of the newe teſtamente, that ſhal be ſhedde for manye for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſynnes. Nowe here haue you harde, how playnly our ſauyour Chryſt hym ſelfe, affyrmeth that his moſte holy and bleſſed bodi bothe fleſhe &amp; blud was really, corporally na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turally
<pb facs="tcp:19485:11"/> and ſubſtancially preſent at this worthy maundy vnder the accedental fourms of bred and wyne. And as thys holye euangelyſte, hath here mooſte truely declared, the maner and fourme of this godlye inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ordinaunce, euen ſoo and no leſſe do al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other thre euangeliſtes &amp; alſo the bleſſed Apoſtle Saynt Paule, whoſe ſayinges at thys tyme I doo here omyt, becauſe I truſte in God, this frutefull declaraty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhalbe ſufficiente vnto you, yf that you wyll with a ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt fayth, open your hart and faythfully receyue and folowe the ſame. And although chriſt alſoſo be in heauen, and ſyttethe at the ryght hand of God the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> yet whoſoeuer ſhal eate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> breade in the ſupper of
<pb facs="tcp:19485:11"/> our lorde, accordyng to Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes inſtitution and ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is aſſured by chryſtes promis and teſtament, that he recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth Chryſtes very body, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſuffered for vs vppon the croſſe. And lykewyſe he that drynketh of that holy cuppe in that ſupper of oure Lorde (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to chryſtes inſtituty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) is certified by Chriſtes le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation and teſtament, that he drynketh the bloude of Chryſt which was ſhed for vs. Soo that no man can contempne or lyghtlye eſteme this mooſte holy and bleſſed communion, excepte he contempne alſo chryſtes bleſſed body &amp; bloud. And becauſe it ſhoulde not be thought, but that thys mooſte godlye inſtytution and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunces,
<pb facs="tcp:19485:12"/> ſhoulde alway here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after be put in vre, and to haue a perpetuall contynuaunce in Chryſtes church to all forces, purpoſes, and effectes, lyke as Chryſte hym ſelfe dyd leaue it, and ſet it fourth vnto vs, at his moſt bleſſed maundy, he went farther with vs, and gaue vs a commaundement and ſayd.<note place="margin">Luc. xxii</note> Thys doo, in remembraunce of me. Now what was Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes mening by theſe two wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des this do, but that we muſt promptlye, fyrmely, and fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye followe hys example &amp; doyng. That is, Take bread, geue thankes breake it, ſaye theſe wordes, Thys is my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> And than eating the ſame <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ate his very bleſſed body. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>kinge the cup and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng
<pb facs="tcp:19485:12"/> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like, we drinke his moſt precious bloude. Here it hath bene ſhewed now, what is vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtand by theſe two wordes Thys do. Now to fynyſhe vp the whole ſentence and ſaying of the Euangeliſt Luke yf we faithfully (this do) than it ſhal folowe that we muſt nedes of verye duetye, and of a very co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gruence call to our reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce not onely this infinite benefit and moſt louyng dede of oure Sauyoure, leauynge here in earthe with vs to oure greate comforte, thys moſte precious treaſour (I meane his mooſte bleſſed body fleſhe and bloud) but alſo by the often receuyng of the ſame, we ſhal daily hour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, and timely, cal to our reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braunce lykewiſe, his mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19485:13"/> paynefull deathe and paſſion which he ſuffered for vs moſte myſerable offenders, to bryng vs to the fruition of his euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting glory. Now here haue you hard alſo this whole text truelye declared.</p>
            <p>Thys do in remembraunce of me. I thynke verelye there is no perſon that wyl be ſo bolde (lokyng a chryſten man in the face wyth open eyes) to ſay or affyrme the contrarye, ſeinge that al the foure Euangeliſts, and alſo the bleſſed Appoſtle Sayncte Paule (declarynge the true and playne fourme and maner of thys godlye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution and ordinaunce) doo ground them ſelues vpon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>lyble truthe, that is vpon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and vppon hys owne
<pb facs="tcp:19485:13"/> wordes, ſayinges, &amp; doinges. And therfore I truſte louinge Syſter, that theſe plaine aſſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cions and manifeſt probatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are ſufficiente for you at thys time, to verefie and proue that Chryſtes bleſſed bodye fleſhe and bloude, is conteyned real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, naturallye, corporally, and ſubſtantiallye, here in earthe wyth vs and amonge vs, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the formes of breade and wyne. Peace, euen nowe me thinke I here you and ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (as it wer behind a cloth) whiſperynge one in a nothers eare, ſaying: What he ſpeketh al to gether againſt the whole courſe of nature, to ſaye that breade and wine is chaunged into fleſhe and bloude, as I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> well it is a whote ſuppe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19485:14"/> you wil let fall, but I am glad that you haue taken vp thys matter, for I truſt (the circum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtaunce well conſidered in the reſoluynge therof) not onelye your muche infidelitie, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo your great ignoraunce will a great deale the better apere, for your inſtruction &amp; amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. I pray you, what though it be againſt nature to chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge bread &amp; wyne, in to fleſſhe and bloude, ſhall not the worde of Chryſte be of that powere, to chaunge and to alter the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of the elementes, aſwel as the grace and bleſſynge of the Prophets did alter &amp; chaunge other thinges againſt nature. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not the grace and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Moiſes of ſuche pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> chaunged a rod into
<pb facs="tcp:19485:14"/> a ſerpent, and the ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t again into a rod.<note place="margin">Exo. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Was not the grace and bleſſynge alſo of the ſame Prophette of the lyke pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, whan it torned the floud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of Egypt from water ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daynely into bloud, and from bloude agayne into water?<note place="margin">Exo. xiiii</note> And lykewiſe was not the grace and bleſſing of this wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy and conſtante prophete of as much power, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Hebrues, were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed aboute on the one ſyde wyth the Egyptians, and on the other ſide with the ſea, and he lyfted vp his rodde, and the water deuyded it ſelfe, &amp; ſtode vppe like a wall, and betwene the waters was left away for him and his company to paſſe on fote, and Iordaine againſt
<pb facs="tcp:19485:15"/> the courſe of nature, tourned backe to the head of his ſpring And in like maner was not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace and bleſſing of Moyſes of great power,<note place="margin">Exo. xvii</note> whan he tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the rocke ſtone and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter came out haboundauntlye which it hadde not of nature?<note place="margin">Exo. xv.</note> Alſo Marathe was a bytter floud, ſo that the people being drye coulde not drinke therof, but whan Moyſes had put a certayne wodde into the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than the nature of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter left his bytternes, whyche grace infuſed dyd ſodaynelye moderate.<note place="margin">iiii. Reg. vi.</note> And lykewyſe how wrought grace againſt nature whan an axe heade fell from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the prophetes ſeruants <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> water, and he that loſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> deſyred the prophet
<pb facs="tcp:19485:15"/> Elyſeus helpe, who put the helfe into the water, and recei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued the yron agayne, whyche thing we playnly knowe was done aboue nature, for yron is heuyar then the lyquor of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? Thus we maye perceyue that grace is of more force and ſtrengthe than is nature. And yet hetherto I haue rehearſed vnto you, nothyng els but the grace of the bleſſyng of the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phetes. Now than yf the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge of men be of ſuche pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that it may or can chaunge nature, what maye we ſaye or what maye we thynke, of the bleſſed conſecration of GOD, wherin is the operation of the wordes of our ſauiour Chriſt? For thys ſacramente whyche we here treat of, is done <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19485:16"/> worde of Chryſte? Than if the worde of Helyas was of ſuche power that it could bryng fyre downe from heauen,<note place="margin">iii. Reg. xvi.</note> ſhall not than the myghtye worde of Chryſte be of that power (yea rather of muche more power) to chaunge and to aulter, the kindes and natures of elemen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes into fleſhe and bloude? The infynyte workes and the incomprehenſyble doynges of Chryſte, may not be meaſured by our humaine reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neyther yet by the courſe of nature, but by the ſpirite of GOD and by ſtedfaſte fayth. What ſaye we of the makynge of the whole world? Rede we not that God ſpake, and the thynges were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He commaunded, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> created? The word
<pb facs="tcp:19485:16"/> than of Chryſte that coulde of nothynge make thynges that were not, can it not chaunge thoſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges that be, into thoſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges which before they were not? For it is no leſſe matter, to geue to thynges newe natu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res, then to alter natures.</p>
            <p>And therefore yf there be ſo muche ſtrength in the wordes of our lord Ieſu, that thynges had theyr begynnyng therby, which neuer were before, how muche more then be they able to worke, that thoſe thynges that were before ſhould rema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine, and alſo be chaunged into other thynges? Thus is a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficyente aunſwere made vnto your whiſteringe for the firſte parte of your fonde oppinyon prouyd vnto you bye no pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phane
<pb facs="tcp:19485:17"/> nouelties, nor diſceitfull aucthorytyes, but euen by the diuyne ſcryptures of antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye. And therfore I moſt har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely exhorte you, worthelye to receyue and enbrace the ſame, and combyne it and lyncke it faſt vnto your ſences, with the fyrme and infregible chaine of ſtedfaſt fayth,<note place="margin">Vincenti.</note> and glutten not your ſelfe wyth the filthy drag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges of hereticall opinyons. For greatly you and all other oughte to feare and to dreade the daungerous puniſhement which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitution &amp; alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cenſurs of the apoſtolyke aucthoritye do threaten vnto you, for that you be ſo lyghtly deceiued and ſeduced by ſwete preachynge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="6 letters">
                  <desc>••••••</desc>
               </gap>eryng wordes, from
<pb facs="tcp:19485:17"/> the grounded veritie of gods moſt holye word, geuyng your ſelues vp to fables hauing da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Ro. xvi.</note> And therfore you ought depely to remember, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to enpreſſe in your harte the feareful and vehement ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge of the bleſſed Apoſtle S. Paule, whyche he wrote not only to the Galathians, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to the vniuerſall churche of Chryſt that for the affirminge and ſtablyſſhing of the faythe, newelye receyued, he neyther auored hym ſelf nor any other of the Apoſtles, but dyd ſo exe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cute his apoſtolical aucthory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that with gret ſeueritie he pronounced theſe wordes and ſayde. Althoughe eyther we, or an angel from heauen prech vnto you,<note place="margin">Gala. i.</note> any other goſpel tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:19485:18"/> that which we haue preached holde hym accurſed.<note place="margin">Vincentius</note> Here it ſuffiſed not this bleſſed apoſtle for the retention, of the true chriſtian fayth (which the vni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſall churche of Chryſte tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughoute the whole worlde, doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe and acknowlege) to touch the condicion and na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture of man (which is mutable variable, and chaungeable, &amp; apte of it ſelfe to decline from the truth) but alſo herein he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prehendeth the angelicall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencye. For althoughe wee (ſayethe he) or an angell from heauen, not meaning that the holye and heauenly Angeles, can preache any euil doctrine. but his meaninge is this. If y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> myght be, which cannot be. And therefore he enlarged his
<pb facs="tcp:19485:18"/> ſpech and ſayd. Whoſoeuer he be that ſhal attempt to chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge and alter the true catholyke fayth lette hym be, ſayethe he, Anathema, that is to ſay, lette him be ſeperated, ſegregated, and excluded as one accurſed, leaſte the dangerous infectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of one corrupte ſhepe, may poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and infect to whole ſound flocke of Chryſt with his vene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mous permyxtion and compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye. And therefore it is not lau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full for you, nor for anye other priuate perſonne, to alowe and folow any other doctrine than ſuch as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> catholike chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, doth vniuerſallye prech &amp; teache. I cannot ſufficientlye wonder at you, and at certain ſuche other,<note place="margin">vincentius.</note> whiche cannot be contented with the auncyente
<pb facs="tcp:19485:19"/> beleyfe, taughte and receyued vniuerſally in Chriſtes church but muſt ſeke daylye for newe toyes and games, euermore coueitinge to alter &amp; innouate the chryſtyan relygion, eyther by addynge ſome thing that is new, or elſe by takyng awaye parte of that whyche was old (as you doo here declarynge your fonde opinion which wil take away chryſtes beinge in earth, becauſe he is in heauen) as though the chriſtian religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the churche were not an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly ordinaunce and decree, but rather an earthly prouiſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and inſtitution. But wo be to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which phantiſie to prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe ſuche rydles and dreames to ſhadowe the glorye of God and his truthe. The bleſſed
<pb facs="tcp:19485:19"/> Apoſtle Sainte Paule, wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to his diſciple Tymothe, did earneſtly counſayle hym &amp; aduertiſe him to forſee and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware, the daunger and peryll of ſuch innouations and alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, whan he wrote theſe wordes and ſayd.<note place="margin">i. Timo. vi.</note> O Timothe kepe that doctrine which was lefte vnto the, and auoyde all prophane nouelties of wordes and oppoſicions of ſcyence falſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſo called. What can be more vehementlye ſpoken or ſayde, agaynſt innouations and alte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rations, contrary to the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciente order of the vniuerſall Churche of Chryſt, than this?<note place="margin">vincentius</note> Yet for al this we ſe the ſtony indurate hartes, the ſhameles impudency, the ſtyffe and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious pertinacye of dyuerſe
<pb facs="tcp:19485:20"/> whom nether the gret waight of ſo manifeſt ſcripturs canne moue to yelde, nor the waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye importans of ſo high auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities can force to retyre, ne yet ſoo terryble threatnynges of hygh vengeaunce can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade to repent. And therfore deare Syſter I would wiſhe you to be none of thys ſorte of people, but rather to be an ear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſte folower of the holſeſome counſell of the bleſſed Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Saynte Paule, where he ſayth as it is before rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Kepe that doctrine which was lefte vnto the, and auoid all prophane nouelties of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and oppoſycyons of ſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence faulſelye ſoo called. Whyche is no more to meane, but that you hold aſſuredly, ye
<pb facs="tcp:19485:20"/> and alſo ſaue and kepe faſt, the inuiolat and pure talent of the catholyke faythe, receyued by the conſent of the hole vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Church of Chriſt, and com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mytted vnto you faythfully to obſerue and kepe. Exchaunge it not for no newe fangeled no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uelties but what you haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued holde that ſtyll and no other. And yf you coapte and apply your ſelfe, to thys ſound and perfect doctrine, than the heauenlye prouydence of God wil not ſuffer you to erre, from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> catholyke ſayth in any point</p>
            <p>For that man or woman is a true and a perfecte catholyke perſon, which loueth the truth of God,<note place="margin">vincentius.</note> whyche preferreth no ſynguler perſons aucthorytye, wytte, loue, affection, iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb facs="tcp:19485:21"/> knowledge or eloquence before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true religion of Chriſt and hys vnyuerſall catholyke fayth. But diſpyſyng all thoſe thynges, dothe abyde perma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, conſtaunt, and ſtable, in fayth, and reſolueth with hym ſelfe to receyue, holde, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue, that whiche he knoweth the catholyke churche vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſallye and continually to haue receyued, holden and beleued.</p>
            <p>Nowe here I entende (after thys littell dyſcourſe) to make an ende of the fyrſte parte of youre phantaſtycall opinyon, where you ſaye that the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed bodye of our ſauiour Ieſu chriſt, cannot be preſently here in earth, and alſo in heauen at one tyme and together, which fonde opynyon of youres for
<pb facs="tcp:19485:21"/> the fyrſt parte, I truſte I haue ſuffyciently approued the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye (that is) that he is here remayning preſently in earthe amonge vs, and wyth vs, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the formes of breade and wyne moſte aſſuredlye bothe fleſhe and bloude. And nowe to proue the other parte, that he is alſo in heauen, it ſhal not be nedefull to bryng the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in queſtion, For I knowe well there was neuer any tru chryſten perſon yet, of chryſtes fayth and beleue, that at anye time doubted thereof, the thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges it ſelfe being ſo cleare, ſoo playne, and ſo manifeſt in the whole body of ſcrypture. And therefore becauſe I woulde not be ſene prolyxe or tedyous vnto you, here I purpoſe to fy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyſhe
<pb facs="tcp:19485:22"/> and conclude this hole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome exhortation for this time And thus much haue I wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vnto you, not for any gret acquayntaunce that I haue had with you, as I ſaid at my beginninge, for I was neuer in your companye more than one ſuppere meale. But the thing that moued me to take this finale labour in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d was partly for that I am now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed (by gods prouidence) to be your pore adioined neigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boure and youre gentell huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonde my very louinge frend. But the cheife and principall cauſe (you ſhall vnderſtande) was for that god hath conduc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted and hyred me with his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye to trauell and to laboure in his vyneyarde,<note place="margin">Mat. xx.</note> not onelye
<pb facs="tcp:19485:22"/> to declare the mutuall bond of charitie, and chryſtyan loue which we chryſtians ought to ſhewe, the one vnto the other for Chryſtes ſake, in tyme of temptation. But alſo to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue his faythfull flocke from the raueuynge mouthe of that monſtruous beaſt, which S. Peter ſettethe fourth vnto vs in his fyrſt epiſtle and laſt cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pyter, ſaying in this wyſe.<note place="margin">i. Petre. v</note> Be ſobere and watch, for your ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſary the deuyll as a roryng lyon walkyth aboute, ſekyng whom he maye deuoure who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reſyſt ſtedefaſt in faithe. And therefore according to the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell of thys holye Apoſtle, lette ſtedefaſt fayth be your ſhylde of defenſe, &amp; ſhake of the wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked armour of the Deuyll (by
<pb facs="tcp:19485:23"/> that I mene) the fylthy ſkorfe and the ſtynking froth of your daungerous opynion, where you dreame and ſaye, that the bleſſed body of our Sauiour Ieſu Chryſt cannot be preſent lye heare in earthe and alſo in heauen at one time and toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſhal perceiue that you do digeſt this holſom preparatyue well (whyche I haue here addreſſed vnto you) than hereafter I wyll not ſeſe (yf nede ſo requyre) to ſend vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to you ſome other godly cordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als to ſtrengthen you with al, So that by the ſame (I truſte in our Lorde) you ſhall fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thys accompte with youre ſelfe that your faith once tried beinge muche more precious than golde,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Petre. i.</note> which is tryed by
<pb facs="tcp:19485:23"/> fyre, ſhalbe founde vnto lande, glorye and honor, at the appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Ieſus Chriſt. But now on the other ſyde, yf you be ſo preciſe and ſoo hardened in your harte, that you will not beleue this my aucthor of tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the (euen Chryſte hym ſelfe) whome I haue here preduced and alledged for my foundati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, but wil haue him tryed by a queſt of wytneſſes, than I wyl endeuer my ſelfe here af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to impanel you ſoo auncy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ente, ſo worthye, and ſo aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tycall a queſt of his moſt true and truſty frendes (vnſpotted vncorrupted &amp; vndefamed) that you ſhalbe faine I doute not, to let youre matter fall to a nonſute, and to beleue ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtlye from thenceforthe that
<pb facs="tcp:19485:24"/> chriſt is preſently here in earth with vs, and alſo in heauen at one time and together. Grace be with you,<note place="margin">Ephe. vi.</note> and with al them whiche loue oure Lord Ieſus Chryſt in purenes and truth. Amen.</p>
            <q>¶ If any man erre from the truthe and another conuert him, lette the ſame know, that he which conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſynner from goinge aſtraye out of his waye, ſhall ſaue a ſoule from death, and ſhal hide the multi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tude of ſynnes. Iames .v.</q>
            <p>Thys brefe exhortation was thus finiſhed and directed to the aboue named Margarete Burges of kyngeſwod by the ſaid Paule Buſhe late Biſhop In the yere of our Lord God, a thouſand, fyue hundred, fifty and ſyxe, The ſeuenth daye of Auguſt, In the yeares alſo of
<pb facs="tcp:19485:24"/> the reigne of our moſte drede Soueraygne Lorde and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, Phylyppe and Marye, oure Kynge and Queene, the third and fourth.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>i. Cor. iii.</bibl>
               <p>¶ Paulus plantauit, ſed deus incrementum dedit.</p>
               <p>¶ <hi>Paule planted, but GOD gaue the increaſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London in Powles Churchyard at the ſygne of the Holye Ghoſte by Ihon Cawodde, Printer to the King and Quenes Maieſties.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cum Priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
